I’m going around the world giving talks about Darwin,
أنني أدور حول العالم ألقي محاضرات عن داروين
and usually what I’m talking about
وفي العادة ما أتكلم عنه
is Darwin’s strange inversion of reasoning.
عن نظرية داروين الغريبة عن السببية
Now that title, that phrase, comes from a critic, an early critic,
هذا العنوان ، هذه العبارة ، أتت من ناقد سابقاً
and this is a passage that I just love, and would like to read for you.
وهذه عبارة أحب واود أن أقراءها لكم
"In the theory with which we have to deal, Absolute Ignorance is the artificer;
"في النظرية التي يجب ان نتعامل معها ، التجاهل الصرف هو أفضل نحات
so that we may enunciate as the fundamental principle of the whole system,
حيث يمكننا الإعلان عن المبادئ الرئيسية للنظام بمجمله
that, in order to make a perfect and beautiful machine,
أنه ، لعمل آله متكاملة وجميلة
it is not requisite to know how to make it.
ليس متطلبا معرفه كيفية صنعها
This proposition will be found on careful examination to express,
هذا المقترح سيتضح بتمحيص دقيق، ليفهم
in condensed form, the essential purport of the Theory,
بالمختصر ، المفهوم الأساسي للنظرية
and to express in a few words all Mr. Darwin’s meaning;
ولطرح في كلمات معدودة كل مفاهيم السيد داروين
who, by a strange inversion of reasoning,
والذي ، عبر عكسية عجيبة للسببية
seems to think Absolute Ignorance fully qualified
يبدو في إعتقاده أن الجاهلية الصرفة مؤهلة تماماً
to take the place of Absolute Wisdom in the achievements of creative skill."
لتأخذ مكان الحكمة لإنجازات المهاراته الإبداعية"ـ
Exactly. Exactly. And it is a strange inversion.
بالضبط تماماً ، وهو تضاد عجيب
A creationist pamphlet has this wonderful page in it:
أحد كراسات المؤمنين بالخلق فيها هذه الصفحة الرائعة :
"Test Two:
إختبار 2
Do you know of any building that didn’t have a builder? Yes/No.
هل تعرف مبني ليس له باني؟ نعم لا
Do you know of any painting that didn’t have a painter? Yes/No.
هل تعرف رسمة بدون رسام؟ نعم لا
Do you know of any car that didn’t have a maker? Yes/No.
هل تعرف سيارة بدون صانع؟ نعم لا
If you answered 'Yes' for any of the above, give details."
إذا كانت أجاباتك "نعم" على أي مما سبق ، أعطي تفاصيل
A-ha! I mean, it really is a strange inversion of reasoning.
أهاا ..!! أنها حقيقتاً عكس عجيب للسببية
You would have thought it stands to reason
أنت قد تفكر أنها تقف لسبب
that design requires an intelligent designer.
أن التصميم يحتاج لمصمم ذكي
But Darwin shows that it’s just false.
ولكن دارون يقول أن هذا ببساطة خطأ..!؟!
Today, though, I’m going to talk about Darwin’s other strange inversion,
اليوم، إذاً ، سأتكلم عن نظرية داروين العكسية الغريبة الأخرى
which is equally puzzling at first, but in some ways just as important.
وهي مساوية في الغرابة بدايةً ، ولكنها بطريقة أخرى مهمة كذلك
It stands to reason that we love chocolate cake because it is sweet.
إنها تقف لتسبيب حبنا لكيكة الشكولاتة لأنها حلوة
Guys go for girls like this because they are sexy.
وأن الشباب يعجبون بالبنات لانهن جذابات
We adore babies because they’re so cute.
وأن نحب الأطفال لأنهم لطيفين
And, of course, we are amused by jokes because they are funny.
وطبعاً كلنا نستمتع بالنكت لأنها مضحكة
This is all backwards. It is. And Darwin shows us why.
هذا كله بالعكس ، وداروين يرينا كيف
Let’s start with sweet. Our sweet tooth is basically an evolved sugar detector,
لنبدأ بالحلو ، شهيتنا للسكاكر هي ببساطة لاقط سكر متطور
because sugar is high energy, and it’s just been wired up to the preferer,
حيث أن السكر طاقة عالية ، وقد ربط عالياً كتفضيل
to put it very crudely, and that’s why we like sugar.
لنستفيد منه بشكله الخام ، ولهذا نحب السكر
Honey is sweet because we like it, not "we like it because honey is sweet."
العسل حلو لأننا نحبه ، وليس "نحبه لأن العسل حلو"
There’s nothing intrinsically sweet about honey.
ليس هناك شي جوهري حلو حول العسل
If you looked at glucose molecules till you were blind,
إذا نظرنا لذرات الجلوكوز حتى نصاب بالعمى
you wouldn’t see why they tasted sweet.
لن ترى لماذا طعمها حلو
You have to look in our brains to understand why they’re sweet.
ولكنك يجب أن تنظر داخل أدمغتنا لتفهم لماذا هي حلوة
So if you think first there was sweetness,
لذا إذا فكرت أولاً أن هناك حلاوة
and then we evolved to like sweetness,
ثم تطورنا لنحب الحلاوة
you’ve got it backwards; that’s just wrong. It’s the other way round.
لقد فهمتوها بالعكس ، أنه ببساطه خطأ، وهي بالعكس تماماً
Sweetness was born with the wiring which evolved.
الحلاوة ولدت برابط تطور لدينا
And there’s nothing intrinsically sexy about these young ladies.
حيث ليس هناك شي جوهري جذاب حول هاؤلاء البنات الشابات
And it’s a good thing that there isn’t, because if there were,
وهي شي جيد أنه ليس كذلك ، لأنهن لو كن كذلك
then Mother Nature would have a problem:
لواجهت الطبيعه الأم مشكلة
How on earth do you get chimps to mate?
كيف ستجعل القرود تتزاوج على وجه الأرض
Now you might think, ah, there’s a solution: hallucinations.
الآن قد تفكرون ، أه ، هنالك حل ، الهلوسات
That would be one way of doing it, but there’s a quicker way.
قد يكون هذا أحد طرق فعلها ، ولكن هناك طريقه أسرع
Just wire the chimps up to love that look,
فقط أربط بمخيلة القرد ليحب ذلك الشكل
and apparently they do.
وكما يبدو إنهم يفعلون لك
That’s all there is to it.
هذا كل ما في الأمر
Over six million years, we and the chimps evolved our different ways.
عبر ستة ملايين سنة ، نحن والقرود تطورنا بشكل مختلف
We became bald-bodied, oddly enough;
نحن أصبحنا أقل شعراُ بقدر ممكن
for one reason or another, they didn’t.
لسبب أو لأخر هم لم يقل شعر جسدهم
If we hadn’t, then probably this would be the height of sexiness.
لو لم نتطور ، لربما أصبحت كثافة شعر الجسد أعلى درجات الجاذبية
Our sweet tooth is an evolved and instinctual preference for high-energy food.
فشهيتنا للحلويات قد تطورت كخيار مفضل للطعام ذو الطاقة العالية
It wasn’t designed for chocolate cake.
ولم تكن مصممة لكيكة الشوكلاتة فقط
Chocolate cake is a supernormal stimulus.
كيكة الشوكلاته هي جاذب فوق الطبيعي
The term is owed to Niko Tinbergen,
المقولة نعارة من نبكو تينبيرقن
who did his famous experiments with gulls,
الذي عمل تجربته الشهيرة مع طيور النورس
where he found that that orange spot on the gull’s beak --
حيث وجد أن البقعة البرتقالية في منقار النورس
if he made a bigger, oranger spot
لو صنع بقعه برتقالية أكبر
the gull chicks would peck at it even harder.
أن أناثي النورس ستنقر عليه أقوى
It was a hyperstimulus for them, and they loved it.
لقد كان منوم جذاب لهن ، فأحبوه
What we see with, say, chocolate cake
ومانراه هنا ، لنقل ، كيكة الشكولاته
is it’s a supernormal stimulus to tweak our design wiring.
أنها جاذب فوق الطبيعي ليعدل تصميم خريطتنا الذهنية
And there are lots of supernormal stimuli; chocolate cake is one.
وهناك العديد من الأشياء الجذابة فوق الطبيعي وكيكة الشوكلاتة احدها
There's lots of supernormal stimuli for sexiness.
وهناك جواذب فوق طبيعيه للحميمية
And there's even supernormal stimuli for cuteness. Here’s a pretty good example.
وهناك كذلك جواذب فوق طبيعيه للطاف ، وهنا مثال جيد
It’s important that we love babies, and that we not be put off by, say, messy diapers.
أنه مهم أن نحب الأطفال ، وليس أن نقرف من حفاظاتهم الملخبطة
So babies have to attract our affection and our nurturing, and they do.
ليتمكن الأطفال من جذب إهتمامنا الطبيعي لتربيتهم
And, by the way, a recent study shows that mothers
وبالمناسبة هناك دراسة تثبت أن الأمهات
prefer the smell of the dirty diapers of their own baby.
يفضلن رائحة حفاظات أطفالهن
So nature works on many levels here.
إذا الطبيعة تعمل هنا على مستويات مختلفة
But now, if babies didn’t look the way they do -- if babies looked like this,
ولكن الآن ، إذا لم يظهر الأطفال كما يبدون ، وظهروا كذلك
that’s what we would find adorable, that’s what we would find --
هذا ما نجده جديراً بالاعجاب ، وهذا ماقد نجده ..
we would think, oh my goodness, do I ever want to hug that.
سنفكر ، يا إلاهي ، هل أنا فعلاً أريد أن أحضن هذا
This is the strange inversion.
هذا تضاد عجيب
Well now, finally what about funny. My answer is, it’s the same story, the same story.
إذاً الآن ، أخيراً ماذا عن الفكاهه ، وجوابي ، أنه نفس القصة
This is the hard one, the one that isn’t obvious. That’s why I leave it to the end.
وهذه هي الصعبة ، الغير ظاهرة ، لذلك أتركها للآخر
And I won’t be able to say too much about it.
ولن يمكنني القول كثيرا عنها
But you have to think evolutionarily, you have to think, what hard job that has to be done --
ولكن يجب أن تفكروا بثورية ، يجب أن تفكروا ، يالها من مهمة صعبة يجب أن تنجز
it’s dirty work, somebody’s got to do it --
أنه عمل صعب ، على أحد أن يفعله
is so important to give us such a powerful, inbuilt reward for it when we succeed.
وهو مهم جدا أن يعطينا عوائد قوية وجوهرية عندما ننجح
Now, I think we've found the answer -- I and a few of my colleagues.
الآن أظن أننا وجدنا الجواب ، أنا وبعض زملائي
It’s a neural system that’s wired up to reward the brain
أنه نظام عصبي مربوط ليجازي الدماغ خيرا
for doing a grubby clerical job.
لعمله هذا الأعمال التنسيقية
Our bumper sticker for this view is
و ملصقنا العام لهذه النظره
that this is the joy of debugging.
هذه هي متعه تحليل الأخطاء وحلها
Now I’m not going to have time to spell it all out,
والآن ليس لدي الوقت لأقولها كلها
but I’ll just say that only some kinds of debugging get the reward.
هناك أنواع معينة من التحليل والإصلاح التي تجد الجزاء الحسن
And what we’re doing is we’re using humor as a sort of neuroscientific probe
وما نفعله حين نستخدم الفكاهه كمفتاح لعلم الأعصاب
by switching humor on and off, by turning the knob on a joke --
يتحويل الفكاهة لموصول ومطفي ، ببرم المفتاح على النكتة
now it’s not funny ... oh, now it’s funnier ...
الآن هي ليست مضحكة ... أووه الآن هي مضحكة
now we’ll turn a little bit more ... now it’s not funny --
الآن سنحولها أكثر قليلاً .. الآن هي ليست مضحكة
in this way, we can actually learn something
بهذه الطريقة ، يمكننا حقيقتا تعلم شي
about the architecture of the brain,
عن تصميم خريطة الذهن
the functional architecture of the brain.
والتخطيط التفاعلي للدماغ
Matthew Hurley is the first author of this. We call it the Hurley Model.
ماثيو هارلي هو أول كاتب لذلك، حيث نسميها طريقة هارلي
He’s a computer scientist, Reginald Adams a psychologist, and there I am,
أنه عالم حاسوب ، و ريجنالك أدامز ، نفساني ، وأنا
and we’re putting this together into a book.
نحن نجمع ذلك سوياً في كتاب
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم